The youthful perspective on the future,
어릴 때 생각한 미래
the present perspective on the future
지금 생각하는 미래
and the future, mature perspective on the future --
그리고 미래의 시점에서 더 어른스럽게 생각하는 미래.
I'd like to try and bring all those three tenses together
저는 그 세 가지 시점을 한데 모아서
in one identity tonight.
오늘 밤, 바로 이 순간으로 가지고 오려고 합니다.
And you could say that the poet, in many ways,
시인에 대해 다들 이렇게 말합니다.
And you ask yourself:
한 번 생각해보세요.
The conversational nature of reality is the fact
현실에 대한 대화본능이란 것은
that whatever you desire of the world --
세상에 바라는 것
whatever you desire of your partner in a marriage or a love relationship,
배우자나 사랑하는 가족에게 바라는 것
whatever you desire of your children,
여러분의 아이들에게 바라는 것
whatever you desire of the people who work for you or with you,
여러분의 직장 동료들에게 바라는 것
or your world --
혹은 여러분 자신도
will not happen exactly as you would like it to happen.
여러분이 바라는 대로 되지 않는다는 사실입니다.
But equally,
그런데 마찬가지로
whatever the world desires of us --
세상이 우리에게 바라는 것
whatever our partner, our child, our colleague,
우리의 배우자, 아이들, 동료들
our industry,
우리 사회와
our future demands of us,
우리 미래가 우리에게 요구하는 것도
will also not happen.
그대로 이루어지지 않죠.
And what actually happens
실제로는
is this frontier between what you think is you
하나의 경계가 생겨납니다.
And this frontier of actual meeting
바로 그 경계점이
is the only place, actually, where things are real.
오직 그 곳에서만 모든 게 현실로 다가오게 됩니다.
But it's quite astonishing,
놀랍게도 우리는
how little time we spend at this conversational frontier,
그 대화의 경계에서 아주 잠깐 동안만 머물려고 하고
and not abstracted away from it in one strategy or another.
어떻게든 거기에서 벗어나 눈에 띄지 않으려고만 합니다.
I was coming through immigration,
입국심사를 통과할 때
which is quite a dramatic border at the moment,
그 순간만큼은 국경을 극적으로 넘는 느낌이죠.
into the US last year,
작년에 미국으로 들어올 때였는데요.
and, you know, you get off an international flight
아시다시피 대서양을 건너 국제선에서 내린 직후에
across the Atlantic,
그리 쾌적한 장소를 만나진 않습니다.
you're not at your most spiritually mature.
정신적으로 안정된 상태도 아니죠.
You're quite impatient with the rest of humanity, in fact.
사실, 인간성도 바닥나서 참기 힘든 상태가 됩니다.
So when you get up to immigration with your shirt collar out
옷 매무새가 엉망인 채로 입국심사장에 도착했을 때에는
and the immigration officer looked at my passport
입국심사관이 제 여권을 보고 이렇게 말합니다.
and said, "What do you do, Mr. Whyte?"
"화이트씨, 직업이 뭐죠?"
I said, "I work with the conversational nature of reality."
"저는 현실의 대화 본능에 관련된 일을 합니다."
(Laughter)
(웃음)
And he leaned forward over his podium
그러자 그는 책상 앞으로 몸을 숙이며 이렇게 말합니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
(Applause)
(박수)
And I said, "I'm sorry,
제가 대답했습니다. "미안하지만..
my powers as a poet and philosopher only go so far.
시인이자 철학가로서 제 능력은 그저 그래요.
I'm not sure I can --"
제가 별로 도움이 될런지..."
But before we knew it,
그런데 어느샌가
we were into a conversation about his marriage.
우리는 그의 결혼 문제에 대해 대화를 나누고 있었습니다.
Here he was in his uniform,
그는 분명 근무중이었습니다.
and the interesting thing was,
재밌는 점은
he was looking up and down the row of officers
그가 주위 심사관들을 둘러보는 것이었어요.
to make sure his supervisor didn't see
일상적인 대화를 나누고 있는 것을
that we was having a real conversation.
상관에게 들키지 않기 위해서였죠.
But all of us live at this conversational frontier
하지만 우리 모두는 이런 대화의 경계에서 살고 있습니다.
with the future.
미래에 대한 대화죠.
I'd like to put you in the shoes of my Irish niece,
아일랜드에 사는 제 조카의 입장에서 한번 생각해볼까요.
Marlene McCormack,
제 조카 말린 맥코맥은
standing on a cliff edge on the western coast of Spain,
스페인 서해안의 절벽 끝에 서서
overlooking the broad Atlantic.
드넓은 대서양을 바라보고 있었습니다.
Twenty-three years old, she's just walked 500 miles
스물세 살 때 그녀는 800 km를 걸어서
from Saint Jean Pied de Port on the French side of the Pyrenees,
프랑스 피레네 산맥의 생장 피에 드 포르를 출발해
all the way across Northern Spain,
북 스페인까지 갔습니다.
on this very famous, old and contemporary pilgrimage
아주 유명하고 유서깊은 당대의 순례 여정이죠.
called the Camino de Santiago de Compostela --
"카미노 드 산티아고 드 콤포스텔라"
the Path to Santiago of Compostela.
'산티아고 드 콤포스텔라로 가는 길' 이라는 뜻의 순례길입니다.
And when you get to Santiago, actually,
실제로 산티아고에 도착하게 되면
it can be something of an anticlimax,
다소 실망할지도 모릅니다.
because there are 100,000 people living there
10만 명이 사는 그 도시의 누구도
who are not necessarily applauding you as you're coming into town.
여러분이 마을에 도착했다고 해서 박수를 쳐 주지 않거든요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
And 10,000 of them are trying to sell you a memento of your journey.
그 중, 만 명은 여러분에게 여행 기념품을 팔려고 할 거예요.
But you do have the possibility of going on for three more days
하지만 그곳에서 사흘만 더 걸어 갈 수 있다면
to this place where Marlene stood, called, in Spanish, Finisterre,
말린이 갔던 곳에 가보세요.
from the Latin, meaning "the ends of the earth,"
"지구의 끝"이라는 뜻의 라틴어입니다.
the place where ground turns to ocean;
육지가 바다로 바뀌는 곳이고
the place where your present turns into the future.
현재가 미래로 바뀌는 곳이기도 합니다.
And Marlene had walked this way --
말린이 걸어온 길은 이렇습니다.
she just graduated as a 23-year-old from the University of Sligo
그녀는 23살에 슬라이고 대학을 졸업했고
with a degree in Irish drama.
아일랜드 연극을 전공했습니다.
And she said to me, "I don't think the major corporations of the world
한 번은 이런 말을 하더군요.
I said, "Listen, I've worked in corporations all over the world
"얘야. 나는 수십 년 동안 전 세계에서 직장 생활을 했는데
a degree in drama is what would most prepare you for the adult --
연극 전공이야말로 재계의 어르신들을 상대하기에
(Laughter)
(웃음)
corporate world."
딱 안성맞춤이지.
(Applause)
(박수)
But she said, "I'm not interested in that, anyway.
그 애가 말했어요. "그런데 저는 전공이 별로 재밌지 않아요."
I don't want to teach drama, I want to become a dramatist.
"저는 연극을 가르치는 것보다 극작가가 되고 싶어요."
I want to write plays.
"희곡을 쓰고 싶거든요."
So I walked the Camino in order to give myself some courage,
"카미노 순례길을 떠났던 것도 스스로 용기를 얻고 싶어서였어요."
in order to walk into my future."
"제 미래를 향해 걷고 싶었거든요."
And I said, "What was the most powerful moment you had on the whole Camino,
"카미노 순례길에서 가장 힘을 얻은 순간이 언제였니?" 라고 물었어요.
the very most powerful moment?"
"가장 힘이 되었던 순간말이야."
She said, "I had many powerful moments,
그 애가 말했어요. "힘이 된 순간은 많았지만"
but you know, the most powerful moment was post-Camino,
"음, 가장 힘을 얻었던 순간은 카미노 순례를 마친 뒤였어요."
was the three days you go on from Santiago and come to this cliff edge.
"산티아고에서 사흘을 더 걸어서 피니스테레 절벽 끝에 갔을 때였죠."
And you go through three rituals.
"도착하면 세 가지 의식을 치러야 하는데요."
The first ritual is to eat a tapas plate of scallops" --
"첫 번째 의식은 가리비 껍질에 담은 파스타를 먹는 거예요. "
or if you're vegetarian,
만약 당신이 채식주의자라면
to contemplate the scallop shell.
가리비 껍질이 좀 신경 쓰이겠네요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
Because the scallop shell has been the icon and badge of your walk,
왜냐하면 가리비 껍질은 순례길의 상징이자 증표 같은 것이거든요.
and every arrow that you have seen along that way
순례길을 따라 놓인 모든 이정표에는
has been pointing underneath a scallop shell.
화살표 위에 가리비 껍질이 그려져 있죠.
So really, this first ritual is saying:
사실 그 첫 번째 의식이 의미하는 것은 이겁니다.
How did you get to this place?
이 곳까지 어떻게 왔는가?
How did you follow the path to get here?
이 곳에 오기까지 어떤 길을 걸어왔는가?
How do you hold the conversation of life when you feel unbesieged,
소외감을 느낄 때 어떻게 삶의 대화를 유지해왔는가?
when you're unbullied,
귀찮게 하는 사람도 없고
when you're left to yourself?
혼자 버려졌을 때는 어떠했는가?
How do you hold the conversation of life that brings you to this place?
스스로 이곳에 오기까지 어떤 삶의 대화를 나누었는가하는 의미죠.
And the second ritual is that you burn something that you've brought.
두 번째 의식은 지니고 있던 물건을 태우는 것입니다.
I said, "What did you burn, Marlene?"
제가 물었죠. "말린, 너는 뭘 태웠니?"
She said, "I burned a letter and two postcards."
"저는 편지하고 엽서 두 장을 태웠어요."
I said, "Astonishing.
"그거, 놀랄 일이네.
Twenty-three years old and you have paper.
스물세 살짜리가 종이를 쓰다니..
I can't believe it."
믿을 수가 없네."
(Laughter)
(웃음)
I'm sure there's a Camino app
저는 카미노 순례길 앱이 있어서
(Laughter)
(웃음)
It will engage the flashlight,
밝게 표시도 해주고
imbue it with color
여러 색으로 구분도 해주고
and disappear in a firework of flames.
그리고는 불꽃놀이와 함께 사라지죠.
But you either bring a letter or you write one there,
하지만 편지를 가져가거나 아니면 그 자리에 편지를 쓴 뒤에
and you burn it.
그걸 태우는 겁니다.
And of course we know intuitively what is on those letters and postcards.
당연히 그 편지와 엽서의 내용이 무엇인지 짐작할 수 있습니다.
It's a form of affection and love that is now no longer extant, yeah?
이제는 집작하거나 애정을 두지 않겠다는 내용이겠죠.
And then the third ritual:
다음으로 세 번쨰 의식입니다.
between all these fires are large piles of clothes.
그 태우는 장소 사이에 옷이 가득 쌓여 있는 곳이 있습니다.
And you leave an item of clothing
그 곳에 오기까지 입었던 것을
that has helped you to get to this place.
거기에 두고 오는 것이죠.
And I said to Marlene, "What did you leave at the cliff edge?"
그래서 말린에게 물었습니다. "너는 그 절벽에 뭘 두고 왔니?"
the very things that I walked in, actually.
제가 걸을 때, 정말 도움이 되었거든요.
They were beautiful boots, I loved those boots,
제가 정말 좋아하는 예쁜 장화였어요.
but they were finished after seven weeks of walking.
7주 동안의 순례가 끝났으니 그 역할을 다 한 거죠.
So I walked away in my trainers,
그래서 운동화로 갈아 신고
but I left my boots there."
장화는 거기 두고 왔어요."
She said, "It was really incredible.
그녀는 이런 말을 했습니다. "정말 놀라운 경험이었어요.
The most powerful moment was, the sun was going down,
가장 강렬했던 순간은..
And the full moon was illuminated by the dying sun in such a powerful way
그리고 그 저무는 해가 보름달을 강렬하게 비추는 거예요.
that even after the sun had dropped below the horizon,
해가 수평선 아래로 가라앉은 뒤에도
the moon could still see that sun.
그 달은 여전히 해를 보고 있던 거죠.
And I had a moon shadow,
달이 저의 그림자를 만들었고
and I was looking at my moon shadow walking across the Atlantic,
계속 보고 있으니 제 그림자가 대서양으로 움직이며
across this ocean.
바다를 가로지르는 거 였어요.
And I thought,
그때 이런 생각이 들었어요.
'Oh! That's my new self going into the future.'
'그래! 나의 새로운 자아가 미래를 향해 가는구나.'
But suddenly I realized the sun was falling further.
그런데 어느 순간, 해가 더 깊이 저물면서
The moon was losing its reflection,
달에 반사되던 빛도 사드라들고
and my shadow was disappearing.
저의 그림자도 사라졌어요.
The most powerful moment I had on the whole Camino
카미노 순례길에서의 가장 강렬했던 순간은
was when I realized I myself had to walk across that unknown sea
나의 미래라는 미지의 바다를 향해
Well, I was so taken by this story,
저는 그 얘기에 빠져들어서
I wrote this piece for her.
그녀를 위해 시를 썼습니다.
We were driving at the time;
우리는 집을 향해 운전하고 있었고
we got home, I sat on the couch,
집에 도착한 뒤, 소파에 앉아서
I wrote until two in the morning --
새벽 2시까지 시를 썼습니다.
everyone had gone to bed --
다들 이미 잠든 시간이었죠.
and I gave it to Marlene at breakfast time.
그리고 아침식사 시간에 말린에게 그걸 건냈습니다.
It's called, "Finisterre," for Marlene McCormack.
말린 맥코맥을 위한 "피니스터"라는 시입니다.
"The road in the end
"길은 끝나고
the road in the end taking the path the sun had taken
그 길 끝은 태양이 지난 길로 향한다.
taking the path the run had taken
그 길 끝은 태양이 지난 길을 향해
into the western sea
서쪽 바다로 이어진다.
into the western sea
서쪽 바다로 이어지고
and the moon
둥근 달 하나
the moon rising behind you
둥근 달 하나가 너의 뒤로 떠오를 때
as you stood where ground turned to ocean:
너는 육지가 바다로 변하는 곳에 홀로 서 있다.
no way to your future now
지금은 너의 미래를 알 수 없지만
except the way your shadow could take,
너의 그림자는 그 길을 향하고 있다.
walking before you across water, going where shadows go,
그림자가 향한 길로 너는 바다를 건너려 하지만
no way to make sense of a world that wouldn't let you pass
이해할 수 없는 이 세상은 너의 의지를 허락하지 않는다.
except to call an end to the way you had come,
세상은 네가 걸어온 길을 끊어 놓고
to take out each letter you had brought
네가 가진 편지를 모두 꺼내 놓아
and light their illumined corners;
물들인 모서리에 불을 붙이라 한다.
and to read them as they drifted on the late western light;
늦은 서쪽 불빛으로 그 편지를 띄워 읽어보라 하고
to empty your bags
너의 가방을 비우라 하고
to empty your bags;
너의 가방을 비워
to sort this and to leave that
가진 것을 나누어 하나를 남기라 한다.
to promise what you needed to promise all along
네가 내내 약속한 것을 지키라며
and to abandon the shoes that brought you here
이곳까지 너를 데려다 준 너의 신발을 포기하고
right at the water's edge,
이곳 물가에 두라 한다.
not because you had given up
네가 포기했기 때문이 아니라
but because now,
이제 너는
you would find a different way to tread,
새로운 길을 찾아 발걸음을 옮기기 때문이며
and because, through it all,
이 모든 걸 견뎌냈고
part of you would still walk on,
너의 일부는 계속 발걸음을 옮기기 때문이다.
no matter how,
무슨 일이 있더라도
over the waves."
저 파도를 넘어서."
"Finisterre."
"피니스터(Finisterre)"
For Marlene McCormack --
말린 맥코맥을 위한 시입니다.
(Applause)
(박수)
who has already had her third play performed
그녀는 이미 세 번째 희곡을 무대에 올렸습니다.
in off-off-off-off-Broadway --
브로드웨이에서 멀리멀리 떨어진
in Dublin.
더블린에서요.
(Laughter)
(읏음)
But she's on her way.
하지만 자신의 길을 걷고 있죠.
This is the last piece.
이것이 마지막 조각입니다.
This is about the supposed arrival at the sum of all of our endeavors.
우리의 모든 노력이 결실을 맺는 도착역이라고 할 수 있죠.
In Santiago itself --
그곳이 산티아고입니다.
it could be Santiago,
산티아고일 수도 있고
it could be Mecca,
메카가 될 수도 있고
it could be Varanasi,
바라나시일지도 모르고
it could be Kyoto,
교토일 수도 있습니다.
it could be that threshold you've set for yourself,
여러분 스스로의 한계일 수도 있고
the disturbing approach to the consummation of all your goals.
목표를 이루기까지의 장애물일 수도 있죠.
And one of the difficulties about walking into your life,
여러분 삶의 여정에서 만나는 많은 어려움 중 하나는..
about coming into this body,
신체적으로나
into this world fully,
살면서 겪는 어려움은
is you start to realize
여러분이 스스로 만든
that you have manufactured three abiding illusions
세 가지 환상에 사로잡혀 있음을 깨닫기 시작하는 것입니다.
that the rest of humanity has shared with you since the beginning of time.
태초부터 우리 인류가 갖고 있던 환상이죠.
And the first illusion is that you can somehow construct a life
첫 번째 환상은
You can somehow be immune to all of the difficulties
자신은 모든 난관과 질병, 상처를 극복할 수 있을 거라는 환상이죠.
that humanity has been subject to since the beginning of time.
그런 것들은 태초부터 우리 인류가 겪어 온 것입니다.
If we look out at the natural world,
자연계를 보더라도
there's no part of that world
세상 어느 것 하나도
that doesn't go through cycles of, first, incipience,
처음 시작된 순환의 고리에서 벗어나는 것은 없습니다.
or hiddenness,
숨겨져 있던 것이
but then growth, fullness,
성장하고 풍성해졌다가
but then a beautiful, to begin with, disappearance,
아름다움이 시들기 시작하고
and then a very austere, full disappearance.
그리고 아주 초라해져 완전히 없어집니다.
We look at that, we say, "That's beautiful,
이렇게 말하곤 하죠.
And when the disappearance is happening,
사그라들기 시작할 때가 되면
I'll close my eyes and wait for the new cycle to come around."
나는 눈을 감고 새로운 순환이 시작되기를 기다리겠어요."
Which means most human beings are at war with reality
이 말은 대부분의 사람들은
The mature identity
성숙한 정체성을 가졌다면
is able to live in the full cycle.
순환의 모든 과정을 살 수 있죠.
The second illusion is,
두 번째 환상은
I can construct a life in which I will not have my heart broken.
자신은 살면서 마음의 상처를 받지 않을 거라고 믿는 것입니다.
Romance is the first place we start to do it.
연애할 때가 가장 대표적이죠.
When you're at the beginning of a new romance or a new marriage,
이제 막 연애나 신혼 생활을 시작할 때 이런 말을 합니다.
you say, "I have found the person who will not break my heart."
"내 마음에 상처 주지 않을 사람을 만났어"라고 말이죠.
I'm sorry;
죄송한 말씀이지만
you have chosen them out unconsciously for that exact core competency.
상대방이 바로 그런 자질이 있기에 무의식적으로 그를 선택한 겁니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
They will break your heart.
그들은 여러분 마음에 상처를 줄 거예요.
Why?
왜냐고요?
Because you care about them.
왜냐하면 여러분이 그에게 집착하기 때문입니다.
You look at parenting, yeah?
다들 자녀가 있으시죠?
Parenting: "I will be the perfect mother and father."
부모들 자신은 완벽한 엄마 아빠가 될 거라고 말합니다.
Your children will break your heart.
여러분 자녀는 여러분의 마음에 상처를 줄 거예요.
And they don't even have to do anything spectacular or dramatic.
그 아이들은 뭔가 대단하고 극적인 일도 하지 않습니다.
But usually, they do do something spectacular or dramatic --
하지만, 아이들이 하는 일은 대개 대단하고 극적으로 다가오죠.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
to break your heart.
그걸로 마음의 상처를 받습니다.
And then they live with you as spies and saboteurs for years,
아이들은 부모와 사는 몇 년 동안은 스파이나 간첩처럼 생활합니다.
watching your every psychological move,
여러분의 심리적 변화를 늘 살피고
and spotting your every weakness.
여러분의 모든 약점을 파악합니다.
And one day,
그러다 어느날
when they're about 14 years old,
아이들이 14살이 되고
with your back turned to them,
여러분이 부엌에서 아이들에게 등을 보인 채로
while you're making something for them --
아이를 위해 뭔가 요리를 하고 있을 때..
(Laughter)
(웃음)
the psychological stiletto goes in.
심리 공격이 들어오죠.
(Applause)
(박수)
And you say, "How did you know exactly where to place it?"
여러분은 이렇게 말하죠. "그게 내 약점인 걸 어떻게 알았니?"
(Laughter)
(웃음)
And they say,
아이가 이렇게 대답하죠.
"I've been watching you for --
"그동안 늘 지켜봤어요."
(Laughter)
(웃음)
a good few years."
"몇 년 동안 쭉 지켜봤죠."
And then we hope that our armored, professional personalities
그리고 우리가 직업적 전문성을 무장하고 있으면
will prevent us from having our heart broken in work.
직장생활에서 상처 받는 일을 막아줄 거라고 기대합니다.
But if you're sincere about your work,
하지만 여러분이 자신의 직장에 애착을 가진다면
it should break your heart.
분명히 상처를 받게 됩니다.
You should get to thresholds
틈림없이 어느 한계에 이르러
where you do not know how to proceed.
어떻게 해야 할지 모르는 때가 오죠.
You do not know how to get from here to there.
어떻게 해결해야 할지 모르는 때가 옵니다.
What does that do?
그러면 어떻게 될까요?
It puts you into a proper relationship with reality.
그때 여러분은 현실과 적당히 타협하게 됩니다.
Why?
왜냐고요?
Because you have to ask for help.
왜냐하면 도움이 필요하기 때문입니다.
Heartbreak.
마음의 상처.
We don't have a choice about heartbreak,
마음의 상처를 받을지 말지 선택할 수는 없습니다.
we only have a choice of having our hearts broken
우리가 선택할 수 있는 것은 마음을 상처를 주는 상대가
over people and things and projects that we deeply care about.
자신이 정말 애착을 갖는 사람, 사물, 혹은 일인지만 선택할 수 있죠.
And the last illusion is,
그리고 마지막 환상은
I can somehow plan enough and arrange things
우리가 계획을 잘 세우고 관리도 잘 해서
that I will be able to see the path to the end
결말까지 잘 이끌 수 있다고 믿는 것입니다.
right from where I'm standing,
자신이 서있는 위치에서부터
right to the horizon.
저 수평선까지 말이죠.
But when you think about it,
하지만 잘 생각해보면
the only environment in which that would be true
실제로 여러분에게 주어진 환경은
would be a flat desert,
광활한 사막일지 모릅니다.
empty of any other life.
다른 생명이 전혀 없는 곳이죠.
But even in a flat desert,
하지만 광활한 사막에서조차
the curvature of the earth would take the path away from you.
지구의 곡률 때문에 길에서 벗어나게 될지도 모르죠.
So, no;
그러니 그래서는 안됩니다.
you see the path,
여러분은 길을 바라보고
and then you don't
눈을 돌렸더라도
and then you see it again.
그 길을 다시 봐야합니다.
So this is "Santiago,"
그 곳이 "산티아고"입니다.
the supposed arrival,
종착지라고 생각하지만
which is a kind of return to the beginning all at the same time.
그와 동시에 시작으로 돌아가는 곳이죠.
We have this experience of the journey,
이것이 우리 여행에서의 경험입니다.
which is in all of our great spiritual traditions,
우리의 위대한 영적 전통인 순례길에서의 경험이죠.
But just by actually standing in the ground of your life fully,
하지만 여러분 인생에서 온전히 육지만 딛고 서서
not trying to abstract yourself into a strategic future
미래에 대한 계획을 세우려 노력하지 않는다면
that's actually just an escape from present heartbreak;
그것은 현실의 마음의 상처로부터 도망치는 것에 불과합니다.
the ability to stand in the ground of your life
여러분의 인생에서 땅을 딛고 서서
and to look at the horizon that is pulling you --
여러분이 마주하는 수평선을 바라볼 수 있다면
in that moment,
바로 그 순간에
you are the whole journey.
그 모든 여정이 끝난 것이고.
You are the whole conversation.
그 모든 대화가 끝나는 것입니다.
"Santiago."
"산티아고(Santiago)"
"The road seen, then not seen
"길이 나타났다가 사라진다.
the road seen, then not seen
길이 나타났다가 사라진다.
the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take
산비탈이 네가 가야할 길을 감추었다가 다시 드러낸다.
the road seen, then not seen
길이 나타났다가 사라진다.
the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take,
산비탈이 네가 가야할 길을 감추었다가 다시 드러낸다.
the road dropping away from you
길이 너로부터 멀어져 내려가고
as if leaving you to walk on thin air,
너는 얇은 공기 위를 걷도록 버려진 것만 같다.
then catching you,
이윽고 길이 너를 찾아낸다.
catching you,
길이 너를 찾아내
holding you up, when you thought you would fall,
긿을 잃었다고 생각할 때면 너를 끌어안는다.
catching you,
길이 너를 찾아내
holding you up, when you thought you would fall,
긿을 잃었다고 생각할 때 너를 끌어안는다.
and the way forward
길은 계속 이어지고
the way forward always in the end
그 이어진 길은 결국 언제나
the way that you came,
네가 왔던 길로 향한다.
the way that you followed, the way that carried you into your future,
네가 걷는 길은 너를 너의 미래로 인도하고
that brought you to this place,
너를 이곳으로 데려온다.
no matter that it sometimes had to take your promise from you,
때로는 너에게 약속을 요구하고
no matter that it always had to break your heart along the way:
언제나 너의 마음에 상처를 줄지라도
the sense
그 감성
the sense of having walked from deep inside yourself
너의 안 깊은 곳에서 걸어나온 그 감성은
out into the revelation,
밖으로 드러난다.
to have risked yourself
위태로운 너를 구해
for something that seemed to stand both inside you and far beyond you,
너의 내면과 외면을 일으켜 세우고
and that called you back in the end
너를 다시 되불러와
to the only road you could follow,
네가 걸을 수 있는 길로 인도한다.
walking as you did, in your rags of love
누더기가 된 사랑의 힘으로 너는 다시 발걸음을 옮긴다.
and speaking in the voice that by night became a prayer for safe arrival,
그 밤에 너의 목소리는
so that one day
그러다 어느날
one day you realized
그 어느 날 너는 깨닫게 된다.
that what you wanted had actually already happened
이미 이루어졌던 것을 네가 바라고 있었음을.
one day you realized
그 어느 날 너는 깨닫는다.
that what you wanted had actually already happened
네가 바라던 것은 이미 이루어진 일이었음을.
and long ago
오래 전에 이루어졌음을.
and in the dwelling place in which you lived before you began,
길을 떠나기 전에 네가 머물던 곳에서
and that
그리고
and that every step along the way,
길을 따라 네가 내딛는 걸음마다
every step along the way,
길을 따라 내딛는 네 발걸음마다
you had carried the heart and the mind and the promise
너의 마음, 너의 생각, 너의 약속이 너와 함께 있었다.
that first set you off and then drew you on,
네가 시작하고 네가 그리던 것들.
and that
그리고
in your simple wish to find a way
길을 찾으려는 너의 소박한 바람.
you were more marvelous
길을 찾겠다는 소박한 바람일 뿐
than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach
네 발걸음이 닿을 곳의 황금빛 지붕이 아니다.
you were more marvelous in that simple wish to find a way
너를 경이롭게 하는 것은 길을 찾겠다는 소박한 바람일 뿐
than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach:
네 발걸음이 닿을 곳의 황금빛 지붕이 아니다.
as if, all along,
어쩌면
you had thought the end point might be a city with golden domes,
네가 줄곧 기대했을 너의 길 끝의 황금지붕 도시와
and cheering crowds,
환호하는 사람들.
and turning the corner
하지만 길모퉁이를 돌아
at what you thought was the end of the road,
길의 끝이라 생각한 곳에서
you found just a simple reflection,
네가 발견한 것은 작은 반영.
and a clear revelation beneath the face looking back
그 아래에서 맑게 드러난 얼굴은 너를 돌아보고
and beneath it another invitation,
그 아래 놓인 것은 새로운 초대장.
all in one glimpse
얼핏 보기에
like a person
사람처럼
like a person or a place you had sought forever
네가 끝없이 찾아온 사람 아니면 장소처럼
like a bold field of freedom that beckoned you beyond;
너에게 손짓하는 광대한 자유의 들판처럼
like another life
또 다른 삶처럼
and the road
그렇게 그 길은
the road still stretching on."
그렇게 그 길은 또 다시 이어진다."
(Applause)
(박수)
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
대단히 감사합니다. 감사합니다.
You're very kind. Thank you.
여러분 모두 감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)